Guide to the Thomas J. Burton research files on Manhattan churches 1822-1982 MS 3219
New-York Historical Society
Thomas J. Burton Research Files on Manhattan Churches
1822-1982
New-York Historical Society
Burton, Thomas J. (Thomas John), 1858-1920
MS 3219
4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
This collection consists mainly of letters, clippings, bulletins, printed programs, sermons, and other ephemera related to church congregations in Manhattan. The material was collected by undertaker and historian Thomas J. Burton (1858-1920) for his book project "History of the Churches of New York, Illustrated," which was apparently never published. Related material collected by others, including E.B. Child (1846-1946), was added to the collection after it was accessioned by the New-York Historical Society.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by name of church.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas J. Burton was born in New York City on October 22, 1858 to Thomas and Sarah Burton. His father was an undertaker, and Burton eventually took over the family business. He was also a member of the executive committee of the New-York Historical Society, and occasionally gave lectures at N-YHS, including illustrated talks about Greenwich Village and Washington Square.
Around 1900, Burton began work on a comprehensive "History of the Churches of New York, Illustrated," which was apparently never published. Writing on the letterhead of the Church History Publishing Company (which shared Burton's home address of 44 East 10th Street), he contacted individual churches and ministers asking for information about the history of their congregations. In 1904, Burton published a pamphlet (available in the N-YHS library) called A Few Old New York Churches and Pastors, which he hoped would "interest any who may have material in their possession...to aid in this collection" "for the purpose of illustrating a contemplated history of New York churches." The replies and materials he received to his entreaties form the bulk of this collection.
Burton died on July 31, 1920 and is buried in Green-Wood Cemetery.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donor information is lacking for this collection. It is likely the Burton material was received between 1920 and 1938. Material from other sources was added later by staff.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists mainly of letters, clippings, bulletins, printed programs, sermons and other ephemera related to church congregations in Manhattan. The material was collected by undertaker and historian Thomas J. Burton (1858-1920) for his book project "History of the Churches of New York, Illustrated," which was apparently never published. Related material collected by others, including E.B. Child (1846-1946), was added to the collection after it was accessioned by the New-York Historical Society.
The type and amount of material available for individual churches varies widely, from a single item to multiple folders of ephemera. Burton was primarily interested in the history and evolution of the church congregations, rather than the physical church structures, and the collection reflects that. There is information about the ministers and leaders of churches, as well as the mergers of various congregations. Although Burton's original collection included images, these were removed by staff sometime before 1950 and added to existing graphic files, mainly the Geographic Collection and the Portrait Collection.
For a preview of Burton's intended project, researchers can consult Burton's 1904 pamphlet (available in the N-YHS library) called A Few Old New York Churches and Pastors, which he hoped would "interest any who may have material in their possession...to aid in this collection" "for the purpose of illustrating a contemplated history of New York churches."
See also Burton's scrapbooks in N-YHS Collection of Scrapbooks. From the finiding aid:"These 3 volumes relate to Burton's work: one volume is a 'catalogue of cuts and illustrations' of churches and ministers; a second volume is mostly notes on the chronology and ministers of various Protestant sects, with various clippings throughout; and the third volume holds clippings with pictures of contemporary (circa 1870-90s) buildings."
Related Materials
N-YHS Collection of Scrapbooks. [MS 3158 Box 30]
A Few Old New York Churches and Pastors, T.J. Burton, N.Y.: 1904
Burton, Thomas J. Papers [BV Burton]
Burton, Thomas J. Correspondence [AHMC Burton]
Churches -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Church history.; Correspondence.; Newspaper clippings.; Printed ephemera.; Child, Edmund Bramhall, 1846-1946
- African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, 1901-1903 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- All Souls Unitarian Church, 1882-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Ascension Episcopal Church, 1925-1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Battery/Bethel/Wesley Methodist Episcopal Church, 1913-1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Bedford Street Methodist Episcopal Church, 1886-1913 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Brick Presbyterian Church, 1856-1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Broadway Presbyterian Church, 1912-1925 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Calvary Episcopal Church, 1837-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Calvary Methodist Church, 1898-1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Canal Street Presbyterian Church, 1894-1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Centenary Methodist Church, 1900-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Central Presbyterian Church, 1902-1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Charles Street United Presbyterian Church, 1879-1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Chelsea Methodist Episcopal Church, 1903 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Chelsea Presbyterian Church, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Christ Church Methodist, 1940-1951 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Christ Church Presbyterian, 1922-1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
- Covenant, Church of the, Presbyterian, 1928-1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
- Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
- First Church of Divine Science, Church of the Healing Christ, 1942-1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
- First Moravian Church, 1894-1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
- First Presbyterian Church, 1846-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23-26)
- First Reformed Episcopal Church, 1874 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
- First United Presbyterian Church, 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
- Fort Washington Collegiate Church, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
- Fort Washington Presbyterian Church, 1914-1938 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
- Fourteenth Street Presbyterian Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
- Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1864-1905 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
- German Evangelical Presbyterian Church, 1892-1901 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- German Society Church, Episcopal, 1875-1882 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Glad Tidings Tabernacle, Pentecostal, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Good Shepherd, Chapel of the, Blackwell's Island, 1920 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Grace Episcopal Church, 1905-1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- Greenwich Presbyterian Church, 1924-1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Harlem Presbyterian Church, 1887-1931 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Heavenly Rest, Church of the, 1945-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Holy Communion, Episcopal Church of the, 1874-1928 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Holy Trinity, Lutheran Church of the, 1896-1926 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Incarnation, Episcopal Church of the, 1895-1953 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- Intercession, Episcopal Church of the, 1889-1905 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
- Jane Street Presbyterian Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
- Jehovah's Witness Watchtower, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
- John Street Methodist Church, 1916-1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  Scope and Contents
  also known as "the Mother Church of American Methodism"
- Madison Avenue Dutch Reformed Church, 1904-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
- Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1888-1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
- Madison Square Presbyterian Church, 1896-1906 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
- Manhattan Congregational Church, 1908-1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
- Marble Collegiate Church, Dutch Reformed, 1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
- Middle Collegiate Dutch Reformed Church, 1822-1953 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  includes a copy of "The pestilence, a punishment for public sins a sermon preached in the Middle Dutch Church, Nov. 17, 1822, after the cessation of the yellow fever, which prevailed in New-York in 1822," by Paschal N. Strong, A.M., 1822.
- Mount Washington Presbyterian Church, 1901-1950 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
- New York Presbyterian Church, 1901-1903 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
- North Presbyterian Church, 1858-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
- Orchard Street Universalist Church, 1865-1901 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
- Park Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1907-1937 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
- Park Presbyterian Church, 1901-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
- Prospect Hill Reformed Church, 1881-1905 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
- Puritans, Presbyterian Church of the, 1891-1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
- Reformed Presbyterian Church, 1897-1941 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
- St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, 1903-1927 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
- St. Andrew's Roman Catholic Church, 1911 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
- St. Ann's/St. Matthew's Episcopal Church, 1853-1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  St. Ann's Church for Deaf-Mutes merged with St. Matthew's Church in 1897.
- St. Augustine, Chapel of, Trinity Church, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
- St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church, 1900-1935 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
- St. Clement's Episcopal Church, 1900 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
- St. Cornelius the Centurion, Chapel of, 1947 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
- St. George's Episcopal Church, 1849-1960 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
- St. James Episcopal, 1880-1957 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- St. James Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- St. James Methodist Church, 1901-1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- St. James Presbyterian Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  One of the earliest Black congregations in New York City.
- St. John's Chapel, Trinity, 1901-1944 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- St. John the Divine, Episcopal Cathedral of, 1919-1941 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- St. John's Lutheran Church/St. Johannes Kirche, 1889-1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- St. John's Methodist Episcopal Church, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- St. John the Evangelist Roman Catholic Church, 1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- St. Mark's in the Bouwerie, 1861-1959 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10-15)
- St. Mary's Episcopal Church, 1901-1954 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
- St. Mary the Virgin, Episcopal Church of, 1937 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
- St. Michael's Episcopal Church, 1889-1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
- St. Nicholas, Dutch Reformed Church of, 1926 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
- St. Paul's Chapel, Trinity, 1886-1937 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
- St. Paul's Chapel at Columbia University, 1931 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
- St. Paul and St. Andrew Methodist Church, 1938-1946 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
- St. Peter's Episcopal Church, 1868-1952 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
- St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, 1901-1977 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
- St. Thomas Church 5th Avenue Episcopal, 1872-1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
- St. Timothy's Church, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
- Second Presbyterian Church (Scotch Presbyterian), 1898-1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
- Sixth Universalist Church of Our Savior/Church of Divine Paternity, 1896-1902 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
- Spring Street Presbyterian Church, 1886-1956 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
- Third Bleecker Universalist Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
- Thirteenth Street Presbyterian Church, 1855-1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
- Trinity Church, 1850-1964 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6-9)
- Trinity Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1946 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
- True Light Chinese Lutheran Church, 1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
- Unification Church, 1982 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  material related to The Unification Church Holy Wedding for World Peace Through Ideal Families, held at Madison Square Garden on July 1, 1982.
- Union Reformed Church, 1902 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
- Washington Heights Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
- Washington Heights United Presbyterian Church, 1901-1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
- Washington Square Methodist Episcopal Church, 1901-1944 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
- Washington Square Reformed Church, 1850-1902 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
- West End Collegiate Church, 1940-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
- West End Presbyterian Church, 1898-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
- West 44th Street United Presbyterian Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
- West Park Presbyterian Church, 1900-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
- Westminster Presbyterian Church, 1899-1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
- Willet Street Methodist Episcopal Church, 1901-1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
- Woods Memorial Chapel, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
- Miscellaneous religious organizations, 1901-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)